A Finding Aid to the Don Raymond David and Andrée Golbin Papers, circa 1920-1980, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Don Raymond David and Andrée Golbin papers
circa 1920-1980
Archives of American Art
David, Don Raymond, 1906-2006
Golbin, Andrée, 1923-2006
AAA.davidon
Archival Resource Key
3.6 Linear feet
The papers of painters Don Raymond David and Andrée Golbin measure 3.6 linear feet, date from circa 1920-1980, and illustrate their lives and careers through biographical material, correspondence, writings, personal business records, printed and photographic material, and artwork.
Biographical / Historical
Don Raymond David (1906-2006) and Andrée Golbin (1923-2006) were husband and wife artists based in New York, NY.
Andrée Golbin was a painter, graphic artist, and illustrator and was born in Germany to her parents Owsey Golbin and Elsa Rimathe, before immigrating to the United States when she was sixteen. She graduated from the Parsons School of Design in 1943 and served as director for Mademoiselle magazine in the early 1950s. Golbin created artwork for many different clients, including several dance companies, Henri Bendel, and American Cyanamid. Golbin was based in New York City and was a member of the Artists Equity Association of New York, the American Newspaper Guild, which she withdrew from in 1948, and the Museum of Modern Art in New York. In her later years, Golbin taught at the Parsons School of Design.
Don Raymond David was a painter and instructor and was born in Springbrook, Yamhill County, Oregon. In 1927, David began studying at Fresno State College with Alexandra Bradshaw and by the late 1930s was in Los Angeles where he studied with Barse Miller and attended the Chouinard Art Institute and the Art Center School. In the late 1950s, he relocated to New York where he attended the Hans Hofmann School and had frequent solo shows at the Camino Gallery through the 1960s to early 1970s. David was an instructor at the Newark School of Fine and Industrial Arts in New Jersey and continued as a teacher beside his wife at the New York Parsons School of Design. He was a member of the California Watercolor Society and the National Society of Art Directors.
Golbin and David died in 2006 in Newburg, Yamhill County, Oregon at the ages of eighty-three and ninety-nine.
Arrangement
This collection consists of seven series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1940-1975 (.1 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1946-1980 (.3 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1920-1978 (.7 Linear feet: Boxes 1-2)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, circa 1951-1977 (.7 Linear feet: Box 2)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1938-1979 (.2 Linear feet: Box 2)
Series 6: Photographic Material, circa 1920-1980 (.3 Linear feet: Box 3)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1920-1980 (1.3 Linear feet: Boxes 3-4, OV 5, and OV 6)
Scope and Contents
The papers of Don Raymond David and Andrée Golbin measure 3.6 linear feet and date from circa 1920-1980. Biographical materials include membership cards to various organizations for both David and Golbin, a graduation certificate for Golbin from the Parsons School of Design, and Andrée Golbin's Who's Who in American Art biographical information. Correspondence is to and from various artists, family members, and organizations and between Golbin and David. Writings consist of various travel diaries, as well as notebooks and lectures for classes taught by David. Personal business records include materials regarding the Creative Artists Public Service Program, dealer contracts, various weekly planners, and price lists for artwork. Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs and announcements, illustrations by Golbin for published works, and prints of sketches. Photographic material includes photographs, slides, and transparencies of Golbin, David, and both artists' artwork. Artwork consists of drawings, sketches, and sketchbooks by both David and Golbin.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers were donated in 1977 by Don Raymond David and in 1981 by Don Raymond David and Andrée Golbin.
Drawings; Sketchbooks; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Educators -- New York (State) -- New York; Diaries
- Biographical Material, circa 1940-1975; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes membership cards to various organizations for both David and Golbin, a graduation certificate for Golbin from the Parsons School of Design, and Andrée Golbin's Who's Who in American Art biographical information.
  - Resume, Don Raymond David, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Membership Cards, Don Raymond David, circa 1948-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Membership Cards, Andrée Golbin, circa 1948-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Parson's School of Design Graduation Certificate, Andrée Golbin, circa 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Who's Who in American Art, Andrée Golbin, circa 1961-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Address Book, circa 1940-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, circa 1946-1980; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; .3 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is to and from various artists, family members, and organizations and between Golbin and David.
  - David, Don Raymond (1940s), circa 1946-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - David, Don Raymond (1950s), circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - David, Don Raymond (1960s), circa 1960-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - David, Don Raymond (1970s), circa 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - David, Don Raymond (1980s), circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Golbin, Andrée (1950s), circa 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Golbin, Andrée (1960s), circa 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Golbin, Andrée (1970s), circa 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
  - David and Golbin (1970s), circa 1971-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Writings, circa 1920-1978; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; .7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Writings consist of various travel diaries, as well as notebooks and lectures for classes taught by David.
  - Design and Layout for Classes, List, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - History of America Illustrations, List of Photographs, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Third Year Illustration", circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Notebooks, Archival Resource Key
    - "Cultural Anthropology", circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "NYC", circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "René Descartes", circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "Wednesday", circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Notes on Art", circa 1920-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Notebook, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Notebook, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Notebook, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Notebook, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Notebook, circa 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Travel Diaries, Archival Resource Key
    - "California", circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "Europe", circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "France", circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "France and Italy", circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Greece", circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "Italy", circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Oregon", circa 1964-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "Oregon and Southwest", circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Oregon Summer", circa 1971-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Oregon Trip", circa 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Spain", circa 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Travel Diary, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lectures, circa 1961-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1951-1977; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; .7 Linear feet Box 2
  Personal business records include materials regarding the Creative Artists Public Service Program, dealer contracts, financial ledgers and various weekly planners, and price lists for artwork.
  - Board of Elections in The City of New York, Certification, circa 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Creative Artists Public Service Program, circa 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, Individual Grant Application, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sherman and Sloane Consignment, circa 1969-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dealer Contracts, circa 1969-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Financial Ledgers, circa 1958-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Weekly Planner, circa 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Weekly Planner, circa 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Weekly Planner, circa 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Weekly Planner, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Weekly Planner, circa 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Weekly Planner, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Weekly Planner, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Weekly Planner, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Price Lists, circa 1952-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Studio Lists, Andrée Golbin, circa 1960-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Art Book Receipts, circa 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Art Sales Receipts, circa 1963-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Art Supply Receipts, circa 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Dance Class Receipts, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Travel Receipts, circa 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, circa 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Printed Material, circa 1938-1979; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; .2 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs and announcements, illustrations by Golbin for published works, and prints of sketches.
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1957-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, David, circa 1940-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Golbin, circa 1950-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Illustrations for Published Works, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - News Clippings, circa 1938-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Press Reviews, circa 1959-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Prints of Sketches, circa 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Photographic Material, circa 1920-1980; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; .3 Linear feet Box 3
  Photographic material includes photographs, transparencies, and slides of Golbin, David, and both artists' artwork.
  - Golbin, Andrée, circa 1930-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Raymond, Don David, Slides, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Personal Photographs, circa 1920-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Personal Photographs, Slides, circa 1967-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Don Raymond David, Archival Resource Key
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Photographs of Artwork, Slides, circa 1965-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Photographs of Artwork, Transparencies, circa 1964-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Andrée Golbin, Archival Resource Key
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1940-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Artwork, Slides, circa 1948-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
- Artwork, circa 1920-1980; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, OV 5, and OV 6
  Artwork consists of drawings, sketches, and sketchbooks by both David and Golbin.
  - Drawings, circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sketches, circa 1920-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
  - Sketches, circa 1930-1980; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
  - Sketches, circa 1930-1980; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
  - Sketchbooks, Archival Resource Key
    - Don Raymond David, Archival Resource Key
      - "Paulet, Vermont", circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - "California", circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - "Los Angeles", circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - "Newark School", circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1975-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1930-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Andrée Golbin, Archival Resource Key
      - Sketchbook, circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Sketchbook, circa 1961-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)